Changes in your diet not
only affect you physically,
physiologically inside,
but also mentally,
how well you think,
psychologically,
how well you feel.
But you’ll never know just
how good you can feel
until you put it to the test
and try eating healthy.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at what plant
based foods have to offer
for the special dietary
demands of pregnancy.
In our first story,
we compare the breast
milk of vegetarian
and non-vegetarian women.
Acompletely plant-based diet
is suitable during pregnancy,
lactation, infancy, and childhood --
a position echoed by the oldest
and largest association of
nutrition professionals in the world.
Ask a couple hundred
health professionals though,
and as few as one in
three appear to know it.
Like any diet during pregnancy,
though, it should be well-planned,
which means consuming large
amounts and a wide variety
of plant foods from
all the plant food groups,
including whole grains, legumes
(like soybeans, regular beans,
split peas, chickpeas, and lentils),
vegetables, fruits,
and nuts and seeds.
Make sure to get enough calcium
from healthy plant-based sources
and sufficient vitamin D
from sun or supplements.
And critically important,
make sure you get
a regular, reliable source
of vitamin B12.
I have a video about B12 in
pregnancy and for kids here.
The two books I recommend
for raising plant-based families,
published by two of my favorite
evidence-based dieticians, are
Your Complete Vegan Pregnancy
by Reed Mangels
and Nourish,
co-authored by Brenda Davis.
What data do we have
on the impact of vegan diet
on pregnancy outcomes?
The vegans had a significantly
lower gestational weight gain
by about six pounds
and lower birthweights,
but just by a few hundred grams,
both about seven pounds each,
within the normal range,
with no differences in the rate
of preterm birth, nor any significant
differences in the umbilical cord blood
B12, folate, or iron marker levels
between the study groups,
not surprisingly since the vast
majority of both groups were taking
prenatal vitamins, as they should.
What about the composition
of breastmilk from those eating
vegan or vegetarian diet?
The systematic review has shown
that all non-vegetarian, vegetarian,
and vegan mothers produce breast
milk of comparable nutritional value.
Even omega-3's?
There was no difference in milk
DHA composition by diet group,
but that's not saying much since
over 80% of study participants
had milk concentrations of long
chain omega-3 DHA below target.
I talk about the best way
to get pollutant-free sources
in a previous video, which we'll
link down in the doctor's note
on NutritionFacts.org or
in the description on YouTube.
The meat and egg industries like
to scaremonger about choline.
But wait, this study was
written by someone
with no conflicts of interest.
Liar!
Here's a corrected version.
The 'Competing interests'
section has been updated.
And surprise, surprise!
The author is a member of a meat
industry funded advisory panel.
The truth is there's just as much
choline in the breastmilk of vegans
as those who eat eggs or meat.
There is something egg-free,
meat-free mothers may not
be passing on as much,
though: industrial pollutants
like the banned pesticide DDT
and cancer-causing PCBs.
The highest levels were found
in the milk of fish-eaters,
and the lowest levels
found in vegetarians.
Even just cutting out meat
may cut DDT stores in half.
For example, here's the levels of
pesticides and carcinogenic PCBs
found in the breastmilk from two
sisters with different dietary habit.
The levels of DDT, DDE (a breakdown
product of DDT), dieldrin,
and beta-hexachlorocyclohexane
(two other banned pesticides),
as well as PCBs, were
much lower in the milk fat
from the lacto-vegetarian
mother than in that
from the non-vegetarian sister.
That's because these chemicals
build up in the food chain
in animal fat, our fat, as well
as any animal fat we eat.
What about mothers
who eat strictly plant-based?
Their milk is even less polluted.
For almost every contaminant,
there was no overlap
in the range of scores,
meaning the highest (worst)
vegetarian value was lower
than the best (lowest) value
obtained in the U.S. sample.
And by vegetarian here,
they mean women who eliminate
all animal products from their diets,
including eggs and dairy.
The one vegetarian mom
who had more than trace amounts
in her breastmilk had only been
veg for less than a year.
But for some of these
other toxic pollutants,
the average vegetarian levels
were only 1 to 2% as high
as the average levels
in the United States.
Breast is still best regardless of
the dietary pattern of the mother,
but nursing infants
of vegetarian women
whose diets are low
on the food chain --
in other words plant-based --
have the advantage of being
exposed to less chemical pollution.
In our next story,
I recommend all pregnant
and breastfeeding women
follow the consensus guidelines
to get about 200mg
of preformed DHA
from a pollutant-
free source.
A systematic review of
randomized controlled trials
of DHA supplementation of pregnant
and breast-feeding women
failed to find any clear and consistent
short or long-term benefit
for psychomotor, mental, visual
or physical development.
Maybe DHA supplementation
during pregnancy has no effect
because the body isn't stupid and
protects the growth of the baby's
brain by drawing off of maternal
stores of DHA, upregulating maternal
DHA synthesis, and preferentially
shuttling it to the fetus.
But what if moms don't start out
with large maternal stores?
In other words, maybe DHA
failed to help women
who were already getting
enough, but maybe women
with very low intakes would benefit
from DHA supplementation.
Well, first it's interesting to note
that even by 1978
researchers were suggesting plant-based
diets as the diet of choice
in the treatment of our
number one killer.
But babies breastfed
by vegan moms
have significantly less DHA in
their bloodstream presumably
because the moms had significantly
less DHA in their breast milk.
The question is whether these
differences are of any consequence?
The growth and development of
vegan and vegetarian children are normal,
as long as they're getting their B12.
No evidence that neural or
intellectual functions are impaired.
In fact the two studies we have
on vegetarian kids
showed that they had higher IQ's,
though that may have been
because their parents tended
to be better educated.
But even though the kids seemed fine,
that doesn't rule out the possibility
that there may be some
subtle differences
in visual or neural
functioning.
It would be interesting to compare
the function of babies getting
vegan breast milk levels versus
general population levels.
You can see vegans had 14,
vegetarians 30, omnivores 37.
This study compared zero
to 32, 64, and 96,
and 32 worked better than zero, but
more than 32 didn't add anything.
This could explain why the general
population at 37 doesn't benefit
from additional DHA supplementation.
But what about down at 14?
Most studies down at that level
showed no advantage over zero,
though one study found a benefit
supplementing at as low as 5,
but that doesn't help us.
Now just because babies
breastfed by vegan moms
have significantly lower DHA
levels in the blood
doesn't necessarily mean they
have lower levels in their brain,
which is where it counts.
What we need is a randomized,
controlled trial in non-fish eaters
of DHA supplementation. Until then,
it's going to remain uncertain.
So what should pregnant
and breastfeeding women
who avoid fish do
in the meanwhile?
Low intakes of DHA
doesn't necessarily equate
with fetal DHA inadequacy,
but this new data suggests that some
infants may not be getting enough
and could benefit from
their moms supplementing.
And so I recommend pregnant
and breastfeeding women
on plant-based diets do follow
the consensus guidelines
to get about 200mg of preformed DHA
from an uncontaminated source
like algae oil, which is probably
the best combination for all women
given the state of our world,
to minimize exposure
to toxic pollutants such as
dioxins, PCBs, and mercury.
Finally today,
we look at the optimal B12 dosage
for kids, pregnant women, and seniors.
Universal improvement of B12 status
appears “to be a nutritional
imperative with possibly
profound beneficial effects,”
particularly at the bookends
of life—at old age and infancy.
I’ve explained the rationale
for my recommendations
to take vitamin B12 supplements
once a week or once a day,
or alternately eat sufficient
daily B12-fortified foods.
But for those over age 65 those
guidelines go out the window.
The recommendations change
to everyone taking
a high daily dose of
1,000 mcg every day.
Starting at age 50 everyone,
meat-eaters and vegans alike,
should be taking B12 supplements
or eating B12-fortified foods.
But over age 65, 50 a day may not do it.
Even 100 a day doesn’t seem sufficient.
Researchers investigated three
doses and found that most
didn’t normalize their MMA until
after the 1,000 microgram dose.
(MMA suppression is a
measure of B12 sufficiency.)
But they just tested 25, 100, and 1,000.
Maybe 250 or 500 would do it?
Researchers set out to find an
adequate dose at that age,
and it seems we need at least about
650 to 1,000 a day in most people,
hence my 1,000 a day
recommendation after age 65.
OK, what about the other
end of the life cycle?
The consequences of B12 deficiency
and insufficiency can be
devastating in
infancy and childhood,
and this is not just a problem
for plant-based pregnancies.
“Vitamin B-12 insufﬁciency during
pregnancy is common
even in nonvegetarian populations.”
About a quarter of all pregnant
women aren’t getting enough B12,
and that number rises to nearly
one in three by the third trimester.
But, insufficiency isn’t as
bad as frank deficiency,
which can manifest in
cases like cerebral atrophy,
meaning brain shrinkage,
in a “Vitamin B12-deficient
Infant of a Vegetarian Mother.”
Thankfully, even severe
brain atrophy can be
substantially reversed with
B12 supplementation,
but better not to become
deficient in the first place.
The solution proposed by a group
of French pediatricians
is to recommend against
raising vegan kids at all,
since B12 supplementation is
necessary. And they’re not alone.
To vegan or not to vegan.
In 2016, two professional
organizations, the U.S. Academy
of Nutrition and Dietetics and
the German Nutrition Society,
issued conﬂicting statements.
The U.S. Academy said that
even strictly plant-based diets
are appropriate for all
stages of the life cycle,
whereas the German group
echoed the French group,
saying since you have to take B12
we can’t recommend a vegan diet
for pregnant women, lactating women,
infants, children, or adolescents.
To confuse the matter further,
the American Academy of Pediatrics
appeared to have it both ways;
in one place repeating
the U.S. Academy’s position, while
in another place it stated that
vegan diets should not
be recommended for children.
But I think they’re just
saying the same thing.
Everyone agrees that a non-B12
supplemented plant-based diet
is a bad idea—that’s part of what
the U.S. Academy means
by “well-planned.”
Everyone eating plant-based,
but especially pregnant
and breastfeeding women, must
ensure a regular, reliable source
of vitamin B12, meaning B12
supplements or B12-fortified foods.
But then you may be able to
get the best of both worlds.
That’s why there are
reviews with titles like this:
plant-based pregnancies:
danger or panacea?
Danger if you don’t take your B12,
but “following a plant-[based] diet
during pregnancy may be protective
against the development of preeclampsia,
pre-gravid obesity, and minimize the
exposure to [DNA-damaging] agents.”
It may also protect our newborns
“from the onset of pediatric diseases,
such as pediatric wheezing,
diabetes, neural tube defects,
orofacial clefts, and some
pediatric tumors.”
“Vegan pregnant women
have a lower-than-average
rate of cesarean section,
less postpartum depression,
and lower neonatal and
maternal mortality,
with no complications or negative
outcomes that are higher than average.”
In addition, a lower incidence
of what used to be called toxemia,
a potentially dangerous pregnancy
complication known as preeclampsia.
“Overall, plant-based diets
seem to confer protection to both
mothers and newborns” by not
only “reducing the risk of several
pregnancy-related issues”, but
decreasing the risk of childhood disease.
“Children following plant-based
diets might have a lower risk
of developing obesity,” obviously
are less exposed to drugs
used in animal production,
and a favorable
anti-inﬂammatory proﬁle
of cell-signaling factors.
But again, everyone on a plant-based
diet has to get enough B12.
Pregnant and breastfeeding
women can just follow
my 50 micrograms a day
recommendation for nonpregnant adults,
or 2,000 a week, though they
suggest breaking up those doses
into two halves to boost absorption.
After infants are weaned, they
can start on 5 micrograms a day;
from ages 4 through 10 they can
take half the adult dose of 25 a day;
and then at age 11 they can
take 50 a day or 2,000 a week.
You don’t have to worry
about taking too much.
It’s water-soluble and you’ll
just end up with expensive pee.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.